there's a press release by the Cleveland
Clinic that makes an argument for the
popular sugar substitute orthol causing
dangerous clotting in our blood
obviously clumping of cells in our blood
can lead to disastrous consequences
since clumps of material are responsible
for blockages in our blood vessels so
what's the rationale here why is the
Cleveland Clinic pointing the finger at
arol a popular sugar substitute found in
gum lower calorie ice creams and other
calorie and carbohydrate conscious foods
and should ariol be avoided based on
these arguments well they're referencing
this new study where in the researchers
uncover some worrying data from some
finally tuned experiments that we'll get
into those shortly first it might be
useful for you to understand a bit of
the mechanisms as in how clotting works
and why orthol might be involved I'll
keep it short but it'll be helpful for
understanding the experiments in short
your blood is filled with many things
from circulating cells to nutrients to
other molecules necessary for life in
your blood you have platelets some might
consider them cells but they're really
more like fragments of cells because
they're missing many cellular components
these platelets circulate through your
blood until they're activated upon
activation they secrete molecules that
activate surrounding platelets and
ultimately Cascade of events occurs that
leads to these platelets to Clump
together this Clump is used to
rudimentarily stick in unwanted openings
and block them think an injury so we
don't lose blood out of our circulation
however they can be activated by other
factors too not just in response to
injury anyway orthol and like molecules
are believed to activate these platelets
by somehow interacting with them and
based on other studies that I've
analyzed here on physionic increase the
activation signals within the platelets
one of those activation signals is
calcium exactly how this happens is not
currently known just know that orthol
somehow directly and possibly indirectly
activates platelets to Clump together
because they are activated at least
that's what's been proposed but let's
look at the data in brief the
researchers recruited healthy young men
and women and them a single dose of
orthol or glucose sugar then they took
blood 30 minutes later and measured the
platelet aggregation remember that's the
clumping of the activated platelets that
we just discussed here's that data I
know it looks like a lot but you
actually know a lot of this without
knowing it as funny as that sounds on
the left side we have the people Fed
ariol so 30 grams and on the right side
we have the people only fled
only flood fed glucose the vertical
axis the ver the vertical axis indicates
the amount of platelet aggregation so
the higher it goes the worse in this
context now the one part that you aren't
familiar with is the ADP concentrations
on the horizontal axis ADP is used to
induce platelet aggregation ADP is a
spent energy molecule I would go more
into that but I don't think it's
pertinent or education here so just know
that our body produces ADP regularly and
it's one trigger for platelet
aggregation by binding a family of
receptors called p2y receptors so the
researchers applied increasing
concentrations of ADP moving left to
right to induce aggregation of platelets
the blue boxes are when people had not
consumed ariol and the red boxes are
when people had the proper comparison
here
is to look at the red versus blue boxes
above each similar ADP concentration the
P values there they indicate that
statistical comparison and if they're
below 0.05 they indicate a statistically
identified increase in clotting or
aggregation with ariol across the board
across all ADP concentrations ariol
increased platelet
aggregation however taking a Peak at the
glucose condition
no effect of glucose they also ran
statistics between the two conditions
called a Freedman test and identified a
difference there too orthol increased
plate aggregation platelet aggregation I
should say compared to glucose 2 there's
some data looking at different markers
of platelet act activation like uh
looking at the release of Serotonin and
platelet factors but I won't Hammer you
with that data it doesn't really make an
appreciable difference on our
interpretation here except that it
confirms the data that we just went over
as ariol increase the release of these
platelet factors just like we described
earlier when platelets secrete molecules
before we get into what we should take
away from all this let me uh bore you
yet again with the information that I
have a premium research review that I
run as a oneman operation and it
includes podcasts on all my
investigations premium videos written
summaries of all my premium videos a
private Community protocols got and much
more it's called the physionic
Insiders if you're so inclined to not
only support my work doing this but also
want access to everything in a
convenient package it's linked in the
description box for you if you're so
inclined okay
so how do we interpret all this does
this change our daily life as you can
tell by the title of the video I'm not
convinced it changes anything but
there's multi multiple reasons for that
one I got a big fat check from the
orthol manufacturers and come on your
boy wants a new Porsche
911 two look at these data again if we
compare the blue and red boxes again the
amount of difference between them is
something like 15 maybe 20% absolute
difference we have to ask ourselves if a
moderate rise in these effects over a
Baseline are that impactful if they're
transient because keep in mind this is
only measured 30 minutes after
consumption we don't know if this
happens uh 1 hour later 5 hours later
and so on also how often are people
consuming orthol at 30 G doses which is
a perfectly normal dose in certain
processed foods like lower sugar ice
cream for example but ariol found in
fruits and other foods are less than 100
mg so an order of magnitude lower third
and importantly the burden of evidence
also requires long-term data we can't
base things on a quasi mechanistic study
even if it is including humans and
healthy ones at that fortunately the
researchers have done some long-term
work which I've touched on in the past
where they indicate blood orthol levels
track with greater incidence of of
cardiovascular events like heart attacks
and stroke however as I mentioned then
and mentioned now there were some
glaring problems with that analysis like
the fact that those with the higher
blood orthol also tend to be sicker that
doesn't even touch on the fact that it
wasn't a measure of consumed orthol only
blood values so what's the takeaway here
this doesn't budge the needle much for
me maybe if you consume large amounts of
ariol every day you may want to cut back
but if you consume orthol in passing or
in small amounts like in gum I probably
wouldn't change anything until we have
better evidence my bribery can continue
on my way to my Porsche and if you're
worried about athol's cousin xylol I
have a video on its supposed heart
disease promoting effects including a
bit more on arrol right here thanks for
tuning in
[Music]